[Music]
all right y'all welcome to scott
horton's show
i am the director of the libertarian
institute editorial director
of antiwar.com author of the book
fool's errand time to end the war in
afghanistan
and i've recorded more than 5 000
interviews going back to 2003 all of
which are available
at scotthorton.org you can also sign up
for the podcast fee
the full archive is also available at
youtube.com
scotthorton show you guys
on the line i've got john kiriyaku
uh he fought the terror wars for the cia
and then they put him in prison
for confirming the identity of some cia
torturers
the only person to be punished for
george w bush's torture program
um you know above officer level anyway
um and uh certainly the only cia
uh officer who was punished and
uh now he's an anti-war guy uh i think
pretty much
fair to say and uh writes created
articles about lots of important things
welcome back to the show john how are
you
thanks doing well thanks good to talk to
you again yeah man
so uh boy there's a lot going on right
now and you got this piece here
a terrible take on the capital storming
and that
is in reference to a former associate of
yours
former cia officer robert grineer whose
uh readers of fool's errand will
remember
was the station chief in islamabad at
the dawn of the terror war
and he gave an interview to npr news
saying this and that about al-qaeda and
the taliban
and the capital mob and the american
right
and some things and i wonder if you
could explain a little bit here
uh maybe even read the quote if you've
got it about
what it is he was getting at there you
know what i'm gonna pull up the quote
what
what he talked about in in a an op-ed in
the new york times
two weeks ago today as a matter of fact
was
uh the fact that we need to treat
events insurrections like we saw in
january the 6th here in washington
uh as insurgencies and
with insurgencies come counter
insurgencies
and i said in my piece that you know
i've known grenier
at all for a very long time and
what he means is we need to be
killing people well killing people for
what reason
i i say in my own piece that
i was as sickened as everybody else was
on january 6th i was as angry as
everybody else was
but we had a demonstration of some 15 or
20 000 people
and we had what 500 800
that actually went inside the capitol
and were violent
and most of them were unarmed i think
that there are accounts of
of three people who we know definitively
were armed
and you're in the new york times saying
that we need to treat this as a counter
insurgency
now what happens in counter insurgencies
is you go door to door and you bust down
the door
sometimes you breach the door with
explosives
you grab everybody inside you
zip tie them or cuff them you take them
to some sort of an interrogation center
and then you just sort it all out later
well we've got this thing called the
constitution
and you can't do stuff like that so you
know
in whatever little way that i could
scott i wanted to lay down a marker and
say
this is wrong this is anti-american
this is a violation of our
constitutional rights
and we've got to put a stop to it i was
disgusted that
the new york times gave him a platform
to even spout this nonsense
yeah you know and i'm so sorry i've been
so buried i got the new book out and
everything i'm gonna send you a copy i
got enough now
um you're on the list what um thank you
but um
alicia i really oh thank you i
appreciate that um i hope you like it
i'm pretty sure you will
um but uh oh
i know so uh my apology was i didn't
even read the new york times article and
i forgot there even was one i read in
your piece that there was one but i
never got around to reading it i only
read the npr
interview after the fact and then
i just got stuck on this paragraph i
just don't know what to do about it and
here's what's so funny
john and man i can't wait to hear what
you have to say about
the giant mess of a question i'm about
to unload on you here okay
first of all here it is uh she says oh
so you were station chief in islamabad
on 9 11. so what are the lessons from
the war against al qaeda there
and you know me i wrote the book about
afghanistan and i'm all hung up on this
point
there's a part in the book where i talk
about how grineer had
uh grenier whatever had organized with
the pakistanis
to prevent friendly fire in case in the
event that bush
allowed delta force to chase after bin
laden when they crossed the border into
pakistan which never happened
um that's kind of part of the role he
played there but anyway
um and that's according to his book 88
days to kandahar where he writes about
all that
but then it's so funny the way he says
this john he goes
and and yes and uh you know even at the
seeming height of the crisis
immediately after 9 11 there really
weren't that many members of
al qaeda in afghanistan and the thrust
of our campaign
there was yes to hunt down al qaeda
but primarily to remove the supportive
environment
in which they were able to live and to
flourish and that meant
fighting the taliban and
and i think that is the heart of what we
need to deal with here
hunting down people who are criminals
that is something which the u.s law
enforcement
is very well capable of doing and doing
while preserving
fundamental civil rights and in some
ways that's the easiest part of the
problem
the difficult part of the problem is
affecting the environment
within which violent elements otherwise
would be able to thrive
so now please allow me to unzip a couple
of things here first of all
i'm stuck on what happened at tora bora
and this son of a is saying that
everything that i said was right
that first of all there were only 400 al
qaeda guys in the country
at the time as cynthia store or his
former cia officer maybe an old friend
of yours i don't know
confirmed to me on this show and that
and then he says
even then even he says it even at the
seeming
height of the crisis immediately after 9
al qaeda was a side project
we decided to go after the taliban
instead okay
so there's that and i want to let you
talk about that for 20 minutes if you
want but then there's the other whole
thing where
he's not even talking about that he's
just making a stupid metaphor
and he's saying that the guys that bum
rush the capital
are al qaeda and the american right
are the taliban yes yes
what the hell so talk about the first
part first though man please
yeah um you know when i was on the
senate foreign relations committee uh
staff we had
we had grenier testify and we had the
chairman of joint chiefs of staff and i
forget who the third person was
but senator jeanne shaheen a democrat
from
new hampshire asked a question and it
was very direct and very pointed
she said and this this was in the spring
of 2009
how many members of al qaeda are in
pakistan
easy question direct question the answer
was 25.
so by 2009 there were 25
members of al qaeda in pakistan we set
out to destroy al-qaeda
in october of 2001
and man they were destroyed so what were
we still doing there
what we've reached that was at the dawn
of the pakistani terror war that was
when obama and the cia were just
starting the drone war there
starting we hadn't even had yet debates
over
refueling the drones for example in
balochistan that became so controversial
you're exactly right so we decided
that we were going to to pick a fight
essentially with the taliban
with which we had never had a beef
right well we didn't have we didn't have
diplomatic relations with them but we
don't have diplomatic relations with a
lot of countries well bill clinton's
government i mean you were in the cia at
the time right isn't it not the case
that bill clinton supported the rise of
the taliban
absolutely absolutely because the
taliban were
anti-communist they were anti-russian
and uh yeah i mean
they it was good for our sphere of
influence
and so this is just five years later
right bill clinton and the saudis and
the pakistanis helped them take kabul in
1996.
this is five years later we're
pretending like i don't know these guys
in fact
let's pretend that the taliban knocked
the towers down while we're letting bin
laden go i mean he even used the word
primarily
immediately after 9 11 our primary
objective was to go after the guys that
didn't do it
and let the guys who did do it get away
john
yep that is exactly what happened that
is exactly what happened
grenier writes in this new york times
piece
and and this is exactly what you said a
moment ago over represented among the
ranks
of angry but ordinary citizens who
stormed the capitol
um on january 6th were others hardly
ordinary
committed to violent extremism the proud
boys the three percenters the oath
keepers
christian nationals chauvinists white
supremacists
and q anon fantasists among others okay
listen
all those groups are nuts i agree all
those groups are nuts they're they're
all extremists
but who says that they were that they
were
committed to violent extremism
i'd like to see what his sources are for
that right or that many oppose a threat
to the american legal order at
all right i mean is there a three
percenter caucus
in one state house out of 50 in this
country no
come on ridiculous
ridiculous and like i say what i said in
my own piece
is i've known grenier for many many
years
decades and this is cia code words
for using violence extrajudicial
violence against
americans hey y'all scott here if you
want a real education in history and
economics
you should check out tom woods's liberty
classroom tom and a really great group
of professors and experts
have put together an entire education of
everything they didn't teach you in
school but should have
follow through from the link in the
margin at scotthorton.org
for tom woods's liberty classroom look
here you and i both know that what you
need is some libertarian institute
things
like shirts and sweatshirts and mugs and
stickers to put on the back of your
truck
and to give to your friends too that say
libertarian institute on them
so that everyone will know the origins
of your oppositional defiant disorder
and where they can listen to all the
best podcasts so here's what you do
go to libertasbella.com and look at all
the great libertarian institute stuff
they've got going there
find the ad in the right hand margin at
libertarian institute dot org
libertas bella.com okay so what are they
really thinking because
okay so here's another part of this
thing that they talk about in this in
the interview
is he says and again this is just crazy
i don't
you know this guy for decades you
explain this to me then
translate this for me kiriakou he says
here's an important element we haven't
talked about is
what i refer to as insurgent leadership
the fact of the matter is
that the most violent elements that we
are concerned about right now
see former president trump as a broadly
popular and charismatic symbol
he is their charismatic leader whether
he chooses to acknowledge it or not
and you know just as i saw in the middle
east
that the air went out of violent
demonstrations
when iraqi leader saddam hussein was
defeated
and seen to be defeated i think the same
situation applies here
the fact that matter is that mr trump
has lost it's very important that people
see that he is lost
is a private citizen but i think it's
extremely important that his potency
as a symbol for the most violent among
us is somehow addressed
in other words we're to somehow perceive
donald trump as sitting at mar-a-lago
leading a continuing insurgency against
the biden government and an attempt to
overthrow it
but we haven't heard a peep from him and
he hasn't said a word after
you know he hasn't put up any kind of
actual fight of any substance
since january 7th he that was the end of
that
you know as far as that goes and
and then again with the analogies here
remember that time john kiriakou that
they captured saddam hussein
and then the next day america defeated
the sunni base insurgency because they
gave up
is that how you remember the year two
thousand four five six and seven and
eight
you know that is not how i remember it
happening
um and he knows better you know bob
grenier is a very smart guy
and he likes to bill himself as the
consummate moderate
but i want to re-read what you just said
here mass demonstrations
in pakistan in support of osama bin
laden fell into dull quiescence when he
was driven into hiding after september
11th
to blunt the extremists mr trump's
veneer of invincibility must
similarly be crushed
now to me scott that that means
to take him out you know take him out
however you
want to politically uh
legally judicially whatever but some
people are going to read that as just
taking him out if you know what i mean
okay so now
so what is going through these people's
head that they're
they must be just pretending to believe
that donald trump is about to what raise
up a brown shirt army
to overthrow all the governors of
america and take over the country or
something give me a break with this
stupidity
this isn't even a comic book well it
says a lot
that as soon as this thing was published
john brennan just
jumped right into the fray on a uh in an
interview on
npr saying that bob grenier is you know
a genius and brilliant and this was a
brilliantly written piece
and we need to stop donald trump and
he's a danger to the republic and all
the usual
garbage that john brennan spouts
this was the plan i mean grenier and
brennan have been friends for
35 years so of course brennan was gonna
come out and uh
and take a cheap shot at trump that's
what we saw happen but the
the scary thing is you know a lot of
people in the cia believe this kind of
thing they believe that they're smarter
than everybody else
they're smarter than you are they're
smarter than i are than i
am and they are going to uh they're
going to put this out there in the
newspaper of record
for all the world to see and uh
they're going to show how the how the
deep state's going to make this whole
thing right
i mean but at the same time they're
tapping his phone and they know he ain't
doing a damn thing
so this is all just make-believe donald
trump
and look if don let's say donald trump
was trying to get real brave right now
all they have to do is send your
replacement down there to have a meeting
with him where hey now that you're a
private citizen again
you think we were hard on you when we
were framing you for treason with russia
we'll cut your throat shut up they'd say
that right to his face
and he would say okay i get it maybe
that's already happened
right i mean there's he's not doing
anything i guess it's possible he could
run again
for the nomination in
election under our laws in another four
years
but other than that he's completely
ridiculous what's he gonna do he's gonna
see south florida
with one armed force you know what are
we talking about
donald trump is like david koresh is
about to march on downtown waco and sees
it
no he's not he's sitting at home when
you guys showed up
he is more concerned right now about the
palm beach city council
asking him to leave than he is about any
kind of
insurrection or or raising a standing
army to attack michigan
or you know whatever else he's being
he's being accused of doing right now
okay but so here's the thing these guys
know they're lying this isn't about
trump this is about picking on the right
it's about kicking the right wing off of
the internet
and as john brennan said even
libertarians
oh yeah who which libertarians ever
insulted john brennan i don't know i'm
sorry guys if i got us all in trouble
uh i saw i chuckled when i read that
yeah well it's not that funny really and
you know antiwar.com has already been
deranked by google
they they rounded us up with the worst
of the right and the left from their
point of view back a few years ago
and they've kicked some of our best
allies completely off
of facebook and twitter um and all kinds
of things
and it seems like it's really only just
starting here but here let me go ahead
and get kind of kooky on you a minute
here for just a second this is the cia
and
you're they say former cia john i don't
know that's the law
they put you in prison i'm pretty sure
if there's a former cia officer you're
one of them
you and ray okay but so aren't
aren't you guys sick and evil and
devious enough that this is all
deliberate because in fact you're not
just trying to kick
not you they are not just trying to kick
the right wing off the internet
they're trying to turn them into a
radicalized force
they're trying to make things worse
they're being provocative
because they're trying to radicalize the
right to have more and more of an excuse
to crack down on them
yes that's exactly what we're seeing
here you know it's funny to me
that that the democrats think that
they're ascendant right now
and so they're overreacting just like so
many of us
predicted that they would but the thing
is this this is always cyclical
and it's going to come back and bite
them and then they're going to be
delisted and then they're going to be
thrown off of
twitter and facebook and instagram and
they're going to jump up and down and
say how unfair it is and how
un-american it it is and then we're back
where we started again
yeah i mean assuming someone can find
their way around silicon valley and all
their restrictions now i mean it sort of
seems like
no we're actually a few miles down the
slippery slope from where we were before
in fact someone interviewing me
yesterday said
doesn't it seem like yeah for those of
us you're a little bit older than me but
for those of us who grew up in the 70s
80s 90s and even 2000s that
that america's over this is a whole
different era now our internet what we
thought the internet would be for
example
which this kind of wide open space of
blogs and retweets and whatever you got
is becoming much more like a
chinese-style internet
and they're going for it and in the name
of this the danger of the white
supremacists which is
apparently the right half of all of
american political culture
yeah you know i don't know right and
it's it's very dangerous
it's very dangerous when and at the in
the meantime we've got these people like
bob grenier
and like uh james clapper and john
brennan
and these other former intelligence
people
coming out and professing to be the
moderates
the right thinkers the ones who are
going to protect us and save us
and if anything they're causing damage
to the constitution
and you know what's hilarious about all
this is this uh i don't know about the
role
of uh grenier here but i know that
john brennan was the
leading backer of jabba al-nusra in
syria
this guy's idea of you know right-wing
radical terrorism
is we ought to help these guys shoot
some tow missiles at some tanks and see
what kind of money and guns and
breakfast and training and whatever else
we can give them
so they can fight better yes
absolutely right we can't forget that it
was john brennan who decided to ally
the cia with al qaeda
which just changed its name to japan
anusura in syria we were actually
fighting on the side of al-qaeda
if you can imagine such a thing yep
and this is the same guy talking about
how you're a trader and i'm a trader
right and and every and you know what
this is exactly what happened after
oklahoma city
right the pac-con operation which one
way or the other
it's not definitive so i won't go out on
a limb it may have been a deliberate
provocation in fact i guess i should ask
you what you know about that but there
was andre strossmeier seems like he was
not really a nazi he was a cop
infiltrating this group and helping
provoke them and then
they did the oklahoma bombing they
blamed it on one or two guys and let the
rest get away
and then they blame the entire right
first of all it was actual nazis that
did it but then they pretended that
they ignored the actual nazis the
literal individual men
who were nazis who did it and instead
they pretended that
all militias are nazis and
and smeared all militias that had grown
up after waco
in response to the waco massacre that
you're not going to do that
around here we'll show you kind of thing
and they said no no these guys all
worship hitler and hate jews and
kill babies now uh after the
uh oklahoma city bombing and they
essentially accuse rush limbaugh who to
me
is the center right you know the
absolute
if he yeah you know not very far right
at all
and it was rush limbaugh and everybody
to the right of him
every white man in america owns a gun
did the oklahoma bombing and slaughtered
those babies
and bill clinton bragged the oklahoma
bombing saved my presidency as
everybody rallied around and and support
the flag and lay a wreath in memory of
the people
and yeah so you know you can see how
dangerous this kind of thing goes
where they want to you know try i mean
it's just like with the muslim terrorist
entrapments too right
there's been as trevor aronson has
documented
there's been between 250 and 300
outright entrapment cases by the fbi
of mostly harmless idiot muslims in
america
loners people with sick mothers in
desperate need of money and
whatever you know trapped into saying
the wrong thing on tape
and and locked in jail um and
you know they can do that same kind of
thing in fact the new law that they're
proposing john
the what i read of it the only thing
that it did i don't think it created any
new crimes that i saw
at least the verse the version of the
bill i saw
um said what it does is it creates a new
domestic terrorism
agency inside the department of homeland
security
and inside the fbi permanent new
agencies to focus on the radical right
which is again the entire
right that's been discussed since the
early 1990s
on my very first trip to london as a cia
officer i'd been to london many times of
course but as
in my first trip as a cia officer we
talked with
mi5 about their duties as a domestic
intelligence service
mi6 is you know famously the foreign
mi5 does only domestic intelligence they
don't have the power to arrest
but they don't need to arrest anybody
that's what scotland yard is for
and the discussions way back then i mean
this must have been 1992 or 1993
we were talking about setting a similar
thing up
in the united states either parallel to
the fbi
or or as a part of the fbi that would
just spy on american citizens
and then provide that intelligence to
the fbi
to affect arrests and here we are
all these years later 30 years later and
it looks like it's going to come to pass
and then but so yeah again it seems like
a step
back to cynthia storer um the
former cia analyst who i interviewed on
the show we were talking about radical
islam and such
and she said that you know she
essentially confirmed that
the what she called the cia's framework
for terrorism for understanding
terrorism what causes it and how to
prevent it and how to short-circuit it
and all these things
it doesn't include religion at all
religion says islam doesn't mohammed all
that has nothing to do with it
whatsoever
it she said it's disenfranchised people
who feel like they have tried
everything and there's no accountability
and no redress
and their voice is silenced and they're
really pissed and then they resort
to if they're you know crafty about it
not just violent revenge attacks but
attacks designed to provoke
political reactions and and move
change forward one way or the other
sometimes into deep chaos before we get
where we're going or this kind of thing
but that that's what it is and if you're
and she was talking i think she was sort
of
i don't even think she explicitly talked
maybe maybe she was
referring to assad at the time that
assad
really could have nipped this thing in
the butt a lot better if he'd been a lot
nicer which i'm not sure i believe that
because there was so much foreign
intervention going on it was too late
for his ass anyway
and i think he knew that too but she was
saying people were just coming out
protesting
and then they got met with real hard
violence and then they really reacted
badly to that and then it's a
a cycle of violence but whether we're
talking about syria where the cia's
intervening
or whether we're talking about anywhere
else that's basically how it goes
so then i'm saying if these guys have
all read the same framework that she's
read
then this seems like early steps in
trying to create a crisis trying to
provoke
some kind of massive violent conflict
that'll lead us to what at the end i
mean it's like they're going to be able
to outlaw
the right-wing party in america or
something like that
and suspend elections from now on and
force us all to submit to
kamala harris is under the new order or
something
so if that's right that they're reading
that same framework the same way and
we're on a
on a john brennan plan for implementing
this thing and making matters worse
deliberately in the short or medium term
to what end other than just
oh good we get to have a new agency and
exercise some more power which is fun
and cash checks and not have to get real
jobs i understand that
but do they have something in mind for
what america is supposed to look like
after the end of four or eight years of
this or worse
you know i don't think they do i think
that for them the end game is
power and authority and all that matters
to them is that they remain in charge
when this is all over
and what you do one of the things that
they taught us scott at the cia
and and from my first week on the job i
i learned this little bit of uh
of uh office politics is that
in order to make yourself as important
as you possibly can you have to
constantly work
at expanding your realm right
you've got to be the king of as many
people as possible and so
so people managers at the cia were
constantly trying to expand their
authority
but when you get up to that level that
senior level of the john brennans and
the bob grenier's
and you want to expand your authority
that expands then into other agencies
i remember in um in 2002
john brennan was in a feud with jim
pavitt who was the deputy director
for operations i worked for jim pavitt
and um
and brennan wanted to be more important
than he was he had been the deputy
executive director
and so they created this new
organization that at the time was called
the ttic
the transnational terrorism information
center it became
the national counter terrorism center
and um and brennan was the first
head well he wanted the t tick to break
off
from the cia and to become its own
agency so he could be
the first head of this new intelligence
agency
not for any other reason not because it
would have streamlined
the information the analysis would have
been any better just because he wanted
to be in charge of his own
little fight them uh and
and have it blocked that well
as it turned out then brennan was the
only person
in 2008 from the cia to join the obama
campaign
everybody else either went to hillary or
to mccain
and uh when obama won the election
brennan was able to call his own uh
his own shot he became the deputy
national security adviser
and then the cia director and then until
until the biden campaign i mean he was
telling everybody in washington who
would listen
that he wanted to be the secretary of
defense the only reason he didn't
become secretary of defense was because
biden was committed to
uh to elevating uh women and minorities
into these senior positions
so it's all about power it's all about
individual authority
it's all about being as important as you
can
possibly be in washington and the
american people be
damned this whole time if that ain't the
theme of the 21st century i don't know
what is
that never even enters the conversation
yeah like that
not even be damned but just not even
brought up to be damned yep
yep that's it by the way
you're in the cia during the 90s tell me
what you guys know
tell me what you know about the oklahoma
bombing from back then john anything
no not a not a single thing not a single
thing of course i was overseas at the
time
i was stationed in bahrain at the time
but um
but this was this was as great
a fbi up as you know
as there's ever been in american history
uh you got that right got that right uh
we got a book coming out i'm not writing
it um
i'll be proud to write the introduction
to it uh a new
uh fellow at the libertarian institute
richard booth who's put together the
ultimate oklahoma city bombing document
archive
uh at oakland at libertarianistic.org
okc by the way um he's writing a book
about it that i think is going to be the
masterpiece
uh and that's going to be we're going to
be publishing that this year
so that is great all right well listen
thank you so much for your time i'm
sorry i'm late i'm supposed to be
talking with danny right now
but uh thank you so much for coming back
on the show i really appreciate it and
listen
uh please stay focused on this and and
writing i know that you understand how
important it is that you have former cia
officer after your name
and um that that means that you can get
people to listen to you on a little bit
higher level
and it's it is important as you
recognize and as you've already taken
the lead in doing
you get right out there and say uh uh i
contradict
my former friend here absolutely not
it's so important to counter this
narrative
with people like yourself on on your
level of credential
in in media terms you know thank you man
i appreciate that very much
oh yeah thanks john appreciate it thanks
you take care
all right you guys that's john kiriakou
he is at consortiumnews.com
the scott horton show anti-war radio can
be heard on kpfk
90.7 fm in la apsradio.com
antiwar.com scotthorton.org
and libertarianinstitute.org
you